Finding Aid for Shirley and Arthur Wolfe Collection of Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands materials, 1952-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Shirley and Arthur Wolfe Collection of Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands materials 1952-2008
Wolfe, Shirley P., collector.
3 linear feet
2010131 Aa 2
Topical files on the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands (Micronesia) and educational materials collected by Arthur and Shirley Wolfe, teachers with United States Department of the Interior for the Truk District Education Department.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Shirley and Arthur Wolfe (donor no. 10296 ) and came to the library in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur and Shirley Wolfe lived in Truk from 1956-1960 and worked as teachers.
The collection includes information on the history of the Pacific Islands; travel brochures and maps; local newsletters and brochures, and materials related to education in Micronesia, specifically in the Truk District. The papers are arranged in the following series: Topical Files, Newsletters and Magazines, and Education.
Subjects:
Education.; Pacific Islands (Trust Territory); Pacific Islands (Trust Territory). Dept. of Education.; Wolfe, Shirley P.; Wolfe, Arthur C.
Contributors:
Wolfe, Arthur C.
- Topical Files
  Topical Files includes information on the history, language, and culture of the Pacific Islands and practical information on living and working in Truk.
  - "Bibliography of Reports, Surveys, and Studies prepared by, for, or about the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands," December 1969 (Box 1)
  - "Code of the Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands," 1956 (compiled by Shirley Wolfe) (Box 1)
  - Government agency memoranda 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Living in Truk 1952-1970 (publications and handbooks) (Box 1)
  - Local events 1957-1960 (invitations and programs) (Box 1)
  - Magazine articles 1964-1995 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Peace Corps program (Box 1)
  - Travel information (maps, hotel information, tour brochures) (Box 1)
  - Trukese language (Box 1)
  - "Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands Administrative Handbook," 1951 (Box 1)
  - United Nations publications 1956 ("Trusteeship Council Report" and "Visiting Mission Handbook") (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications (brochures, booklets, and reports, including "I Shall Return," by Br. Gerard W. Shade, S.J., undated) (Box 1)
- Newsletters and Magazines
  Newsletters and Magazines includes publications of various entities in the Pacific Islands.
  - "Friends of Micronesia," 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - "Highlights" 1971-1978 (Office of the High Commissioner, Trust Territory of the Pacific Islands) (Box 1)
  - "Micronesian Counselor" 2004-2008 (Box 1)
  - "Micronesian Support Committee Bulletin" 1975-1984 (Box 1)
  - "Micronesian Reporter" 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - "Micronesian Reporter" 1959-1980 (Box 2)
  - "South Pacific Bulletin" 1958-1961 (Box 2)
  - "Truk Tide" 1956-1960 (Truk District Government employee biweekly), 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1954-1983 (Box 3)
- Education
  The Education series includes administrative guides and handbooks; curriculum materials; and student reports from the Truk District, the Pacific Island Central School, and the neighboring districts of Palua and Ponape.
  - Pacific Islands Central School
    - Catalogues and handbooks (Box 3)
    - Curriculum materials circa 1956-1958 (Box 3)
    - Newsletter circa 1957 (Box 3)
    - Student reports 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      (includes some autobiographical comments recalling the Japanese occupation of the Marshall Islands in World War II)
  - Palau District teacher handbook (Box 3)
  - Ponape District 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Truk District
    - Elementary curriculum materials (Box 3)
      (includes instructional materials written by Arthur Wolfe for Trukese students and locally produced publications about the Trust Territory)
    - Intermediate
      - Curriculum materials 1957, 1960 (Box 3)
      - "Star of the Sea" 1956-1958 (occasional student newsletter) (Box 3)
      - Student Guide 1957 (Box 3)
    - Orientation materials 1969 (Box 3)
    - "Truk Review" 1956-1960 (occasional newsletter) (Box 3)
    - Visitors' Handbook 1959 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous reports and memoranda (Box 3)